{"Criminal Litigation":[
  {
   "id": "1",
   "question": "All the following are classified as courts of general criminal jurisdiction except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "State High Court",
    "b": "Federal High Court",
    "c": "Magistrate Court",
    "d": "Customary Court"
   },
   "answer": "Federal High Court",
   "reason": "The Federal High Court is classified as a court of special criminal jurisdiction. Others include the court martial, juvenile court."
  },
  {
   "id": "2",
   "question": "At the end of proceedings that day, the Judge said: “The Court will now___”",
   "options": {
    "a": "Stand",
    "b": "Close",
    "c": "Rise",
    "d": "Arise"
   },
   "answer": "Rise",
   "reason": "Rise is the proper word used."
  },
  {
   "id": "3",
   "question": "The appropriate procedure to compel the attendance of a person to answer to a misdemeanor in Court:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Warrant",
    "b": "Arrest",
    "c": "Summons",
    "d": "Writ"
   },
   "answer": "Summons",
   "reason": "Misdemeanor is a simple offence, and summons is usually used for simple offences. One key difference between a summons and a warrant of arrest is that the former is directed to the suspect, while the latter is directed to a third party, usually the police."
  },
  {
   "id": "4",
   "question": "The following except one are circumstances where a warrant of arrest may be used:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Where the law provides that an offender may be arrested without a warrant",
    "b": "Where summons has been disobeyed",
    "c": "Where the law provides that an offender shall not be arrested without a warrant",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the above",
   "reason": "The circumstances where a warrant of arrest is used includes where a law provides that an offender may be arrested without a warrant, where a law provides that an offender shall not be arrested without a warrant and where summons has been disobeyed."
  },
  {
   "id": "5",
   "question": "A male cannot search a female but a female can search a male",
   "options": {
    "a": "True",
    "b": "False",
    "c": "All of the above",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "False",
   "reason": "The current position of the various Administration of criminal justice Laws is that a person can only be searched by member of the same gender"
  },
  {
   "id": "6",
   "question": "All but one of the following are constitutional rights of a suspect at the police station:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Right to a fair trial",
    "b": "Right to remain silent",
    "c": "Right to presumption of innocence",
    "d": "Right to dignity of his human person"
   },
   "answer": "Right to a fair trial",
   "reason": "Trial is not conducted by the police but by the Court. So, right to a fair trial is available to an accused when he is tried by a court or tribunal."
  },
  {
   "id": "7",
   "question": "The following are conditions to be fulfilled before a confessional statement will generally be held admissible, except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "It must be voluntary",
    "b": "It must be made in writing",
    "c": "It must relate to admission of guilt by the accused",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "It must be made in writing",
   "reason": "It is not a condition precedent that a confessional statement must be made in writing before it can be admissible. In Arogundade v State, the written confessional statement made by the accused was discarded while the oral one was used to uphold his conviction. See Sec. 15(5) ACJA."
  },
  {
   "id": "8",
   "question": "______ is where the list of all exhibits in the custody of the police in a particular station or division is recorded",
   "options": {
    "a": "Exhibit register",
    "b": "Exhibit book",
    "c": "Exhibit file",
    "d": "Exhibit diary"
   },
   "answer": "Exhibit register",
   "reason": "Exhibit record of all exhibits in a particular division are kept."
  },
  {
   "id": "9",
   "question": "Under the Magistrates Court Law of Lagos 2009, how many grades of Magistrate Courts exist in Lagos?",
   "options": {
    "a": "None; section 92, MCL",
    "b": "None; section 93, MCL",
    "c": "Five; section 93, MCL",
    "d": "Five; section 92, MCL"
   },
   "answer": "None; section 93, MCL",
   "reason": "By virtue of section 93 of the Magistrate`s law of Lagos state 2009, there are no more grades of magistrate`s"
  },
  {
   "id": "10",
   "question": "Which of these Courts does not have original criminal jurisdiction?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Court of Appeal",
    "b": "High Court",
    "c": "Upper Area Court",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Court of Appeal",
   "reason": " The Court of Appeal and the Supreme Court do not have original criminal jurisdiction. This means they cannot sit as the Court of first instance in any criminal case. Section 239(1) CFRN"
  },
  {
   "id": "11",
   "question": "The member of a Court Martial who must be a qualified legal practitioner is the",
   "options": {
    "a": "President",
    "b": "Liaison Officer",
    "c": "Judge Advocate",
    "d": "Waiting member"
   },
   "answer": "Judge Advocate",
   "reason": "See Section 133 (6)AFA"
  },
  {
   "id": "12",
   "question": "The ICC has jurisdiction to try the following offences except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "War crimes",
    "b": "Crimes against humanity",
    "c": "Kidnapping",
    "d": "Aggression"
   },
   "answer": "Kidnapping",
   "reason": "Kidnapping is not one of the offences that can be tried by ICC. At the close of the prosecution's case in the case of COP v Maja Simons before a Magistrate sitting in Igbosere, Lagos, the defendant opened his case and relied on the defence of mistake in the charge of being in possession of a stolen property. Immediately the defendant closed his defence, the prosecution fearing that he has clearly proved nothing, announced in open court that it has decided to withdraw the case. The Magistrate allowed it."
  },
  {
   "id": "13",
   "question": "The effect of Nolle prosequi by the Attorney General is one of the following:",
   "options": {
    "a": "It amounts to a discharge of the defendant",
    "b": "It amounts to an acquittal of the defendant",
    "c": "The defendant can be tried for the same offence upon fresh evidence being discovered",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "It amounts to a discharge of the defendant",
   "reason": "The effect of Nolle prosequi is that it is a discharge thus, the defendant can be tried on the exact same issue again."
  },
  {
   "id": "14",
   "question": "The charge in Magistrate court of Kano State is prepared by",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Magistrate",
    "b": "The Police",
    "c": "The State Counsel",
    "d": "Any of the above"
   },
   "answer": "The Magistrate",
   "reason": "Magistrates are responsible for preparing charges in the Magistrate Court in the North."
  },
  {
   "id": "15",
   "question": "In which of the following jurisdictions is consent to prefer a charge or file an information no longer needed?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Lagos",
    "b": "Abuja ",
    "c": "Ogun",
    "d": "A and B"
   },
   "answer": "A and B",
   "reason": "In Lagos and Abuja (ACJA and AJJL), consent to file an information is no longer applicable. Thus, the AG or other prosecutorial authority can institute an action against the accused without seeking any consent."
  },
  {
   "id": "16",
   "question": "The rule of drafting charges which admits of no exception is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Rule against ambiguity",
    "b": "Rule against duplicity",
    "c": "Rule against misjoinder of offenders",
    "d": "Rule against misjoinder of offences"
   },
   "answer": "Rule against ambiguity",
   "reason": "The rule against ambiguity is absolute and does not admit any exception."
  },
  {
   "id": "17",
   "question": "Statutory forms is not an exception to the following rules except",
   "options": {
    "a": "Rule against ambiguity",
    "b": "Rule against duplicity",
    "c": "Rule against misjoinder of offenders",
    "d": "Rule against misjoinder of offences"
   },
   "answer": "Rule against duplicity",
   "reason": "Willie John v The State where the Supreme Court justified the use of Form 16 of the Schedule to CPA to charge for housebreaking and stealing in one count."
  },
  {
   "id": "18",
   "question": "What is the maximum or total life span of a remand order under ACJA?",
   "options": {
    "a": "56 days",
    "b": "48 days",
    "c": "30 days",
    "d": "50 days"
   },
   "answer": "56 days",
   "reason": "A remand order under Acja is for 14 days at first instance, then extendable for another 14 days with good cause and two extra 14 days before the person would be released on bail. 14 days into four is 56 days"
  },
  {
   "id": "19",
   "question": "The constitutional right of an accused to an interpreter is contained in______ of the Constitution?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Section 36(5)",
    "b": "Section 36(6)(e)",
    "c": "Section 36(4)",
    "d": "Section 36(6)(d)"
   },
   "answer": "Section 36(6)(e)",
   "reason": "Section 36(6)(e) of the 1999 CRFN provides for the right to have an interpreter when the defendant doesn't understand the language of the court (English)"
  },
  {
   "id": "20",
   "question": "The power to grant pardon can be exercised by:",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Attorney General of the Federation/State",
    "b": "The Chief Justice of Nigeria",
    "c": "The President/Governor",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "The President/Governor",
   "reason": "The power to grant a pardon can only be exercised by the President or the Governor. Section 175 and 212 of the 1999 Constitution."
  },
  {
   "id": "21",
   "question": "To commence criminal proceedings in the Magistrate Court of Lagos State, which of the following is most appropriate?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Complaint on oath",
    "b": "First Information Report",
    "c": "Information",
    "d": "Charge"
   },
   "answer": "Charge",
   "reason": "The only way of commencing criminal proceeding in a Magistrate Court in Lagos is by charge"
  },
  {
   "id": "22",
   "question": "Which of the following is a means of compelling the attendance of a witness in a Magistrate's Court?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Witness summons",
    "b": "Warrant of arrest",
    "c": "Subpoena",
    "d": "Bench warrant"
   },
   "answer": "Witness summons",
   "reason": "Witness is used in the Magistrate Court to compel the attendance of a witness in Court. A magistrate does not have the power to issue a subpoena."
  },
  {
   "id": "23",
   "question": "The types of plea bargain do not include:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Sentence bargain",
    "b": "Conviction bargain",
    "c": "Charge bargain",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Conviction bargain",
   "reason": "There are two types of plea bargain: charge bargain and sentence bargain (see s.494 ACJA, s.75 ACJL Lagos)"
  },
  {
   "id": "24",
   "question": "You witnessed criminal proceedings during your court externship programme. You observed a lot of things.From your observations, in what order were the defendants arraigned?",
   "options": {
    "a": "The defendant was placed on the dock unfettered; the charge was read and explained to him and he was asked to plead",
    "b": "The defendant was placed in the dock fettered, the charge was read to him and he was asked to plead",
    "c": "The charge was read to the accused and he was asked to plead",
    "d": "All of the above"
   },
   "answer": "The defendant was placed on the dock unfettered; the charge was read and explained to him and he was asked to plead",
   "reason": "The order arraignment is as follows: the accused is placed in the dock unfettered, the charge is read and explained to him in the language he understands and he is then asked to take his plea. Sunmabo v The State"
  },
  {
   "id": "25",
   "question": "The judicial authority which emphasised the need for the presence of an accused person throughout criminal trial is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Olabode v State",
    "b": "Olasupo v State",
    "c": "Adeoye v State",
    "d": "Adamu v State"
   },
   "answer": "Adeoye v State",
   "reason": "They are exceptions to this rule for example, where the fine/ punishment is small; where the defendant is of unsound mind; where the hearing is for an interlocutory application."
  },
  {
   "id": "26",
   "question": "Only one of the following totally clears the criminal records of an accused person:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Amnesty",
    "b": "Power of release from prison by the Chief Judge",
    "c": "Pardon",
    "d": "Nolle prosequi"
   },
   "answer": "Pardon",
   "reason": "The effect of pardon is that it clears the criminal record of the convict, and he will be deemed not to have committed the offence he was convicted of. Falae v Obasanjo"
  },
  {
   "id": "27",
   "question": "The right to counsel is a constitutional right provided for under",
   "options": {
    "a": "Section 36(6)(a) 1999 CFRN",
    "b": "Section 36(6)(b) 1999 CFRN",
    "c": "Section 36(6)(c) 1999 CFRN",
    "d": "Section 36(6)(d) 1999 CFRN"
   },
   "answer": "Section 36(6)(c) 1999 CFRN",
   "reason": "You can also use this section to back up the position of legal practitioners at the Area court i.e Right of Audience"
  },
  {
   "id": "28",
   "question": "In total, a remand order can be applied for_____times and each lasts for _____days under ACJA",
   "options": {
    "a": "4 times, 12 days",
    "b": "4 times, 14 days",
    "c": "3 times, 12 days",
    "d": "3 times, 14 days"
   },
   "answer": "4 times, 14 days",
   "reason": "Section 296 of ACJA. Application for Remand is by Motion ex-parte"
  },
  {
   "id": "29",
   "question": "Which of the following is not a factor the court will consider in granting or refusing to grant bail to an accused?",
   "options": {
    "a": "The economic condition of the accused.",
    "b": "The gravity of the offence",
    "c": "The likelihood that accused will tamper with investigation",
    "d": "The likelihood that accused will commit another offence if granted bail"
   },
   "answer": "The economic condition of the accused.",
   "reason": "In Bamaiyi v. The state, the court outlined some factors that might affect granting bail. This is different from conditions for bail."
  },
  {
   "id": "30",
   "question": "In Youngman v COP the conviction of the accused person was set aside because",
   "options": {
    "a": "The charge was defective",
    "b": "The right to fair hearing was breached",
    "c": "The accused had already served the punishment while awaiting trial",
    "d": "A fresh plea was not taken after amendment of the charge"
   },
   "answer": "A fresh plea was not taken after amendment of the charge",
   "reason": "The procedure after amendment of a charge are as follows: New charge will be read to the defendant; Defendant will plead to new charge; The court will enquire if the defendant is ready to be tried and if not, adjournment; The charge is endorsed"
  },
  {
   "id": "31",
   "question": " It is to ______ that all the prosecutorial powers in a State are subject to",
   "options": {
    "a": "The Chief Law Officer of the Nation",
    "b": "The Chief Judge of the State",
    "c": "The Judiciary",
    "d": "The Commissioner for Justice"
   },
   "answer": "The Commissioner for Justice",
   "reason": "The Attorney General of a State is the Commissioner for Justice of that State. Section 195 and 211 CFRN"
  },
  {
   "id": "32",
   "question": "The ICC is composed of how many judges?",
   "options": {
    "a": "15 Judges",
    "b": "16 Judges",
    "c": "17 Judges",
    "d": "18 Judges"
   },
   "answer": "18 Judges",
   "reason": "The International Criminal Court was established on the 1st July, 2002 and they have jurisdiction for the following offences: Genocide; Crime against humanity; War crimes; Crime of Aggression"
  },
  {
   "id": "33",
   "question": "The following offences can be tried at any time by the Court Martial except:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Mutiny",
    "b": "Murder committed outside Nigeria",
    "c": "Desertion",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the above",
   "reason": "Sections 45 - 103 of the Armed Forces Act covers offences created by the Act while sections 104- 114 covers Civilian Offences"
  },
  {
   "id": "34",
   "question": "Customary Courts have original criminal jurisdiction in respect of the following offences except",
   "options": {
    "a": "Cases of violations of bye-laws",
    "b": "Offences for which jurisdiction is expressly conferred on them by law",
    "c": "Contempt ex facie curiae",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Contempt ex facie curiae",
   "reason": "The jurisdiction of Customary Court includes contempt committed in facie curiae and not one committed ex facie curiae. Section 19 of the Customary Courts Law of Oyo State. See also Part II, Schedule to the FCT Customary Court Act, 2007."
  },
  {
   "id": "35",
   "question": "In Lagos, a confessional statement made orally is:",
   "options": {
    "a": "Inadmissible",
    "b": "Partially admissible",
    "c": "Admissible, but less weight is attached to it",
    "d": "At the discretion of the trial judge"
   },
   "answer": "Inadmissible",
   "reason": "Oral confession is inadmissible in Lagos. Section 9(3) ACJL Lagos."
  },
  {
   "id": "36",
   "question": "If officers recovered items including weapons of burglary not covered in a search warrant that was issued. What is the status of the weapons recovered in evidence?",
   "options": {
    "a": "Generally admissible if relevant",
    "b": "Generally inadmissible",
    "c": "Generally admissible whether relevant or not",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "Generally admissible if relevant",
   "reason": "Items not covered in a search warrant recovered in the course of a search are generally admissible provided they are relevant. Section 14 and 15 of the Evidence Act, Musa Sadau v State"
  },
  {
   "id": "37",
   "question": "None but one is a court of special criminal jurisdiction",
   "options": {
    "a": "High Court",
    "b": "Magistrates Court",
    "c": "National Industrial Court",
    "d": "Customary Court"
   },
   "answer": "National Industrial Court",
   "reason": "section 254C(5) CFRN confers criminal Jurisdiction on the National Industrial Court"
  },
  {
   "id": "38",
   "question": "Which of the following courts has no criminal Jurisdiction",
   "options": {
    "a": "National Industrial court",
    "b": "Customary court",
    "c": "Customary court of Appeal",
    "d": "Court of Appeal"
   },
   "answer": "Customary court of Appeal",
   "reason": "The customary court of Appeal has no criminal Jurisdiction so appeals from customary courts go to the Magistrates"
  },
  {
   "id": "39",
   "question": "One of the following is a purpose of raising no case submission",
   "options": {
    "a": "To save the time of the court",
    "b": "To save cost",
    "c": "A and B",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "A and B",
   "reason": "No case submission attacks the evidence adduced by the prosecution"
  },
  {
   "id": "40",
   "question": "One of the following is not a circumstance where the court may grant bail in capital offence ",
   "options": {
    "a": "Extra-ordinary delay in investigation, arrainment and prosecution",
    "b": "Ill health of the defendant and such has been confirmed by a Govt hospital and the prison lacks facility to handle it",
    "c": "Other exceptional circumstances",
    "d": "None of the above"
   },
   "answer": "None of the above",
   "reason": "Section 161(2) ACJA provide for circumstances where the High court may grant bail in capital offences (only high court can do this)"
  }
  ]}
